Vedant Patel

linkedin.com/in/vedant42 Github

A Full Stack Developer with 1.5 years of professional experience, specializing in Java based applications developement, interface design, data security and continous improvement. Coordinating effectively with development teams, clients, and non-technical stakeholders to execute requirements and deliver solutions. Solid grasp on Data Structures and Algorithms, backend as well as frontend Development, Object Oriented Designing and RESTful APIs development.

EXPERIENCE

Full Stack Developer Aug 2022 — Present

First Republic (APIs integration, Testing, Performance optimization, Software Development)

Remote

- Developed complex web applications and services to support First Republic's business operations.
- Collaborated with stakeholders, analysts, cross-functional teams to gather requirements and translate into technical solutions.
- Integrated kafka connect, reduced failure rates by 5%, ensuring efficient message processing.
- Optimized database structures and queries, resulting in a 25% improvement in data retrieval performance.
- Integrating with external systems and APIs to facilitate seamless data exchange.
- Maintained existing Java applications, addressing user inquiries, resolving defects, and implementing enhancements.
- Leveraged springboot to create different modules featuring business rules and workflows.

Full Stack Developer (Fulltime)

Jan 2020 - Aug 2021

Examity (System architecture, Debugging, Continuous integration, microservices, scalability)

India

- Participating in Agile development processes, including sprint planning, stand-up meetings, and retrospective sessions.
- Utilized OOP principles, design patterns, software architecture concepts to create robust solutions.
- Contributed in deploying web services on servers, minimizing downtime, spearheading scalability for application development.
- Implemented code splitting and necessary feature to enhance overall responsiveness and load times.
- Designed responsive user interface, optimized website performance for multiple devices resulting in a 10% decrease in bounce rate.
- Developed POCs (Proof of Concepts) to create an interface between Back end to Front end with mongodb, node.js, and react.js.

PROJECTS

Persona Based SocialBot,

Jan 2022 — May 2022

- Handling documentation, including technical designs, architecture diagrams, and implementation details for future reference.
- Analyzed 6000 json data using python and its latest libraries.
- Improved a perplexity from 300 to 40 and outperformed other models.

Multilevel Feedback Queue Scheduler,

Nov 2021 — Dec 2021

- Implemented an Advance Scheduler to balance threads' different scheduling needs in C.
- Conducted rigorous testing on 100+ unit tests, debugging, and troubleshooting to resolve and decrease bug reports by 50%

Text-To-Speech Application,

May 2019 — Dec 2019

- Led the team of 5 to design and develop a java-based application to build responsive user interface and enhanced performance.
- Applied Java's built-in libraries or and external APIs to generate high-quality speech output with a total 3 customizable voice options.

SKILLS

Methodologies SDLC, Agile Methodology, Waterfall Model.

Programming Language Java, Python, C, C++, SQL, Typescript, ASP.NET, C#, php

Frameworks Spring, Spring MVC, Hibernate, Spring-Boot, Node js, React js, Express, Vue.js

Web Technologies HTML, CSS, XML, JavaScript, AJAX, JSP, Angular, JQuery, Bootstrap.

J2EE Technology Servlets, JSP, JSTL, JavaBeans, JDBC, Maven, Gradle.

Application Server Apache, Tomcat, Java Server.

Database Management MySQL, PostgreSQL, NoSQL, SQL, MongoDB, Oracle, DB2

IDEs Eclipse, NetBeans, Visual Studio code (VsCode)

Version Control Git, Github.

Other Skills CI/CD, parsers, UML, Scrum, Microservices, Docker, Kubernates, Kafka, Junit.

Operating Systems Windows 10, Linux, UNIX

Cloud Amazon Web Service (AWS), Azure, Google Cloud

EDUCATION

Master of Science, Computer Science, University at Buffalo, The State University of New York, GPA: 3.70/4.00

Aug 2021 — Feb 2023 July 2016 — June 2020

Bachelor of Technology, Information Technology, Nirma University, GPA: 7.73/10.00